<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Iesuites play at Lyons in France as it was there presented. Both to the amazement of the beholders, and the destruction of the actors, in August last past. Credibly informed by a factors letter (who was an eye witnesse) to his right worshipful maister in London.</title>
            <author>R. S., fl. 1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851546</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851546</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11253)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 858:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Iesuites play at Lyons in France as it was there presented. Both to the amazement of the beholders, and the destruction of the actors, in August last past. Credibly informed by a factors letter (who was an eye witnesse) to his right worshipful maister in London.</title>
                  <author>R. S., fl. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Nathaniel Butter, dwelling in Paules Churchyeard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: R.S.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the second line of title ends: Ly-.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  France --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Ieſuites play at Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in France, as it was there preſented.</p>
            <p>BOTH <hi>To the amazement of the Beholders,</hi> and the deſtruction of the Actors, in <hi>Auguſt laſt paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Credibly informed by a Factors <hi>Letter (who was an eye witneſſe) to his right</hi> worſhipful Maiſter in London.</p>
            <p>At London, Printed for Nathaniel Butter, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Paules Churchyeard, 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who euer hath ſeene rebellions diſcouered, he that hath knowne that Traitors liue like Moles, who worke vnſeene till they be thrown vp to their deaths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and liue abroad like Flyes who ſucke the ſweete of others, yet infect them, ſhall find by this diſcourſe that Religion is made the Target to defend Treaſon: Ambition, the Originall, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the end. Yet for thy further ſatisfaction (Reader) that this diſcourſe &amp; euery particuler relation therein, may haue credit in thy iudgement, know, that there is nothing therein mentioned, but is to be approued by diuers Merchants and men of credite, now reſident in this Citty, and that in reading thereof, thou maiſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to thy ſelfe, that this wonder and ſtroke of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vpon them, is reuealed and ſent vnto thee as a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning peece ſhot off, to admoniſh thee that thou fall not into the preſumption into which theſe Ieſuits and their Deſciples run headlong. I haue as in a map or Dutth Lanskip, ſhewed thee a Module in half an howers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, of what held them two dayes in action: as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the place where they played, the forme of their repreſenting heauen and hell, the dignitie wherein the Actors ſat, the cauſes wherevpon they prepared this iudgement: namely, Ambition (whoſe end is alwaies as theirs was, deſtruction) In any part of which, if thou beeſt eyther ſatisfied or admoniſhed, my paines were a pleaſure vnto mee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16824:3"/>
            <head>The Ieſuites Play at Lions in France.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I receiued your letters and commodities, dated the ſeauenth of Auguſt laſt, and haue diſpatcht that buſineſſe, which by your letters you commanded me, I haue paid <hi>I. P.</hi> the ſixe hundred French crowns, according as you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and haue receiued a diſcharge of him, and dd. the goodes you ſent, marked with the character of * to <hi>I. L.</hi> onely I cannot receiue according to the Factors promiſe to you, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hee pointed at <hi>Paris.</hi> The commondities you ſent for, hold yet the ſame benefite, as my laſt Letters ſpake of. I haue diſtributed all your wares, and looke according to their day, (as I am your Factour) for your money: onely I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receiue, though with my beſt labours, that debt due vnto you (and you charge mee to bee countable of, of <hi>F. G.</hi> though a merchant that holds his auncient preheminence: your profites
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16824:4"/>
which I writ vnto you of, are ſtill good, onely if it may pleaſe you, adde to them at your next ſending, the commodities marked in the latter end of my laſt letter. And I pray ye pay the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change bill to that Gentleman, whom I found in my affaires profitable, ſo as vnto my maiſter both in my beginning and in my ending, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my humbleſt duety vnto you. Yet ſir, if you will giue my idlenes that leaue, to vſe, my ſelfe, and to make practiſe for my experience and your benefite, I ſhall be bolde to vſe ſo much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as to amaze you at that which made mee wonder, the act is as ſtrange as the ſubiect, for God was abuſed, his ſeruants threatned, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies diſplayed, and conſtancie ourthrown.</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhal in this ſcarſe make you think my words being but from a ſeruant haue ſufficient credite, becauſe you would thinke, that in men, who beare ſhew of Diuinity in their ſoules, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in their tongs, I, and ſee me lines in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r habite, would offer ſo great an outrage to the deitie of God, to the derogation of his ſaints, I, and to the diſhonour of Princes, who, if they ſerue him, are his people and miniſters. Then ſir to excuſe my ſelfe, that I was an eye witnes, I hope this ſhall ſerue: to ſee all, becauſe I may vſe the beſt, for without hauing experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the moſt, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be a ſeruant for your good: for you know ſir factors (becauſe your worthy ſelf haue bin one) as they haue many eies that looke into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo they ſhold haue vnderſtanding to preuent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16824:4"/>
danger. If you condemne me for ſeeing of their play, I will excuſe it with this, I am Gods ſeruant, &amp; the kings ſubiect, <hi>Naſcimur pro patria,</hi> ſo as I am born to obey God, I am borne to inſtruct my Countrey, of which ſir we are both members.</p>
            <p>The Ieſuites of France, and poyſon of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld, who liue like Iuie, which doth hurt in growing, in a cheefe Citty of France, the Citie Lions, being as it were a teeming mother, and cheefe nurſe vnto them, and being baniſht from that Country for a murther intended againſt this king <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt laſt, after much and great ſute to his Maieſtie, made their backe repaire, where hauing preached that without folowing their ſteps, their charity, their deuotion, their bleſſings, their curſings, their pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, their praiers, nay all their ordinances, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull people muſt attaine to heauen, &amp; by no other way, which they perſwaded confidently vnto (ſince they who inſtructed them herein, bare humilitie in their lookes, decencie in their apparell, God in their tongues, though Hypocriſie in their harts) both liued and died by their direction, looking after no other ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Thus ſir in my iudgement, and I hope your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will credit, they are bewitched men, in ſteade of God, they ſerue the diuel, &amp; thus blinded poore people they runne headlong to their owne damnation, yet as we are Chriſtians &amp; imitate our Sauior Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, I pittie their miſerie, pray for their conuerſion, and if your patience will but read, Ile report you a wonder moſt true, becauſe mine eies did witnes it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16824:5"/>Theſe Ieſuits comming back into France, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as heretofore the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ory of their religion was builte, vpon the publiſhing of the labours of Saint <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> the ſufferings of Saint <hi>Lawrence,</hi> the troubles, trauailes and charitie of another, ſpreading by turnes their Legend ouer, and ripping vp the whole fardle of their ſuperſtitions, I, and to make them glorious, whome their owne Church had canonized: but cuſtome ſince making them more bolde, to geue you newes to wonder at, that men who bare the ſhew of ſanctitie as they doe, who ſeemes to bee as heauens Trumpets to proclaime the will of heauen, ſhould dare as they haue done, as it were to diſpoſſeſſe God of his throne, to wreſt the ſworde of iuſtice from his almighty hand, and vndertake to bee iudges of others, who ſinfull (miſerable men) haue in their vials not ſo much oyle of vprightnes, as to giue them true light to looke into themſelues.</p>
            <p>Sir, the Subiect of their late play, was the day of Iudgement, that general Seſſions, before which ſhal goe a floud of fire to deſtroy the world, to which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels muſt be ſummoners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not mortals, where diuels (which of thouſand yeeres haue bin ſo) ſtand ready to catch ſoules vnto their torture, and not Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, who by their preſent ſinnefull actions, make themſelues ſo, when all thinges ſhall determine, but theſe two, eternall happineſſe, and perpetuall paine, this fearefull tune, this burning howre, which makes the ſtrongeſt ſhake, but euen to thinke on it.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ieſuites (whom I ſir, being inſtructed in true faith by you, may rather call diuels) preſume to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16824:5"/>
faſhion their ſceane in. Thinke then this play to be at Lyons, their ſtage built in their Colledge, galleries round about, at the foure corners foure tents pitcht as a tyring for the Actors, the Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers many, but theſpectators infinite.</p>
            <p>Firſt, at the 4. corners, figuring the 4. windes, 4. trumpets ſounded, when preſently drummes ratled like to thunder hidiouſly, their in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted fire works flew forth like l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtning, he I did ſeeme to open, and ſmoake roſe from thence: after which, as the fit child of ſuch a wombe, iſſued out flakes of fire, ſhreekings were heard beneath &amp; muſicke aboue, and at one inſtant, many in the ſhape of fiends roſe from below, ſome hauing whippes in their hands, ſome forks, ſome ſnakes, all roaring caſt their eyes vpwarde, at which a Cloude, ſeemed to diuide it ſelfe, the forme of which cloud was thus, Two ſilken vailes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpreade, ſhewed like a Raine-bow, figuring all colours both in heauen and earth, and on the toppe, and intermixt betweene, were ſpang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtarres of golde, as rich, as beautifull. This ſpred, a place was ſeene that repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heauen, the glories of which Palace, as no tongue can expreſſe, ſo was the riches they had vſurped there as infinite.</p>
            <p>Vpon the top of this throne, ſat a reuerend Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite called father <hi>Petronia del Silua,</hi> a Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, the prefect of the Ieſuits colledge, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the perſon of God, &amp; from whoſe mouthal things were queſtioned &amp; determined. And on
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16824:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his right hand ſat father <hi>Maueſta</hi> the 2. Ieſuit in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> rule of houſe, named father <hi>Layola del Cruche,</hi> of a beautifull preſence correſpondent to the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imagined, repreſenting God the ſon.</p>
            <p>And on the left, ſat a beautifull faire Nunne taken out of the Nunnery of ſaint Clare, named <hi>Apolonia del Cruche,</hi> deſcended of the great and illuſtrious houſe of the Boneuenty, &amp; ſhe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the perſon of the Virgin Mary the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Chriſt, whome they termed <hi>A mediatris</hi> and Queen of heauen. About all them thronged Angels all in white, crowned: beneath their feet ſat Prophets and Apoſtles, and many figuring Martyrs, vpon whoſe breaſts were Croſſes red like blood, bearing a ſword in one hand, and a key in the other, crowned likewiſe: vnder which Emblems this was to be read, <hi>I fought, I fought, and gayned,</hi> meaning therby, as (ſo the plaiers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it) they fought againſt ſin, they ſought heauen, and gained a crowne.</p>
            <p>Where after much Muſicke, &amp; many Hymnes of ioy, where on the other ſide there was how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; much fire works: vpon a ſudden all was whiſt, and Time entred, who being called vpon by the Iudge, was commanded to turn back the rolles of his records, and ſhew the preſent world what had bin paſt: which being done, that act conſiſted of the deſtruction of Cities, the ruine of kingdomes, and the downfall of Princes.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Agathocles</hi> of a potter, who had wrought in clay, obtained to graſpe a Scepter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16824:6"/>
               <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of a Tyrant became a Schoolmai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter. How <hi>Cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ida</hi> was faire: yet her p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y and vnconſtancie, made her foule and lepro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>How <hi>Tamberlane</hi> but at firſt a ſhepheard, and keeper of all creatures the ſimpleſt, did after compell kings to draw his Chariot: and Baiaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſirnamed the great, to feed in a Cage.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Layes</hi> was a wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore, yet wiſe men and Philoſophers did dote on her. The morall of all, which was, time is vncertaine, beautie is but a ſtrumpet, who being truſted will deiei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: ſtrength but a Reed, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the leaſt wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſhakes, and ſuch men as thinke themſelues moſt wiſe, proue oftentimes the moſt fooles.</p>
            <p>This act ended, inſtead of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Muſicke to prepare another, the Diuels rored, which being checked by the frowne of the vpper Iudgs, they all hung downe their heads, and were ſilent, who finding time to ſpeak, dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the canfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance: at which <hi>Lucifer</hi> (as it ſeems being thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in that blacke Synod) &amp; as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as his fate to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt, ſo from the reſt he had the fortune to ſpeake firſt, and ſhe wing his dutie (although hee was a diuell) after obeyſance made, refur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they came not in that power fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their low Empyre by the call of his trumpets, to heare Time rehearſe to them things ſo longpaſt, as of <hi>Agathocles, Tamberlane,</hi> and <hi>Layes,</hi> for hee was certaine, they were all, or the moſt part of them there preſent in his army, but their apera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was and deſire now is, to haue a concluſion of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16824:7"/>
world, &amp; their Empyre made vp, they would bee no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to take thoſe they could find, knowing that in the ſifting from the Cradle to the Craſie, both in Court City &amp; country, the greater ſhare to be his. In brief, he eſteemed his Empire ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g enough, and could bee content now to haue hell gates cloſed vp, which had ſtoode open ſo many thouſand years, and might neuer be ſhut, ſoules had preſt ſo faſt into them: Nay, he was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that ſhould the world go vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her hinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer, there would be no room left, creaturs of all ſorts came thronging ſo faſt thither.</p>
            <p>At which, the Iudge with a ſpeaking frowne ſeemed to rebuke the diuell that would Tutor him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the maker of all, how to diſpoſe of any, and that it fitted not him whom he hated to aſk that of him, which he had not pertooke to thoſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Angels whom hee loued: namely, the revolution of the worlde, though in his ſecrete knowledge he had determined of that hour long ſince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As which period ſit, as if indeed hell had beene brooke looſe, the diuels made the greateſt roare they could, and downe they ſunke.</p>
            <p>When the Iudge aboue demaunding for a Booke, which hee called the regiſter of mens ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſpake thus to the aſſembly at his feete. You whom I loue, &amp; ſharers in my glory, whoſe owne deſerts brought you this happineſſe, and makes me ioy in it, within this book all treaſons which the worlde and worldly men haue done againſt heauen, I haue ingroſt, and looking in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16824:7"/>
it, find the volume ful and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nth man that is iuſt to vs. I long ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> put my mercy in the ſcale, in ſtead of wrath, as greening they ſhould periſh, theſe hands created, ſo that through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope of youth &amp; ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>age, their vice is gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e to cuſtom, they haue awaked our anger, &amp; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our peaceful ſoule, we will no longer ſee iniquity and ſuffer it, or honor them with life, bleſſings, &amp; our mercy, which ſo diſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> all, but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we wil receiue our ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nts in to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and curſe the rebels down to hel, a laſting damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. At which the foure Trampeters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as if they had heard their Eue, founded again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ls di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> departing fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> interi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Time, who was Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whole play expreſt thus, that thoſe four Angels were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t to, the foure Elements, to confine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. of them, in the place of their Empery nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, dyre, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d water, but to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty to the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the moſt raging to tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nize ouer the reſt, which charge of his in that twinkling performed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Time ſtooping to the world, intreated the ſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tors to conceiue that the hour paſt, was as ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible as the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Seſſions, and that fire and Brimſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one had rained from heauen to confound mankind, that the time was now come ſo long ſince prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of, when the earthly glory of Princes ſhould determine, and the pride of the beautifulleſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that men ſhould ſecke for ſhelter in the deepes but finde none, that the wretched ſtung with the worme of their owne conſciences,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16824:8"/>
ſhould deſire mountaines to fall, and hils to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, from the reſiſtles wrath of that great, glorious and upright iudge, nor was it now with the world, being en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tred with flames, (the Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y and armor of the almighty) like the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dging of a City, when men ſought to ſaue their poſſeſſions, for now they ſeek to ſhun them.</p>
            <p>The Vſurer whoſe golde was his God, and in whome he putteth hes truſt, ſaw that now it deceiued him, his foundation was rotten, the winds roſe, and his buildinge fell, his riches melted before his face, being tried in this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its againſt the reflection of the ſunne, and reminding by what corruption hee had purchaſed them, he began to curſe the time that euer he ſaw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The vnconſcionable wiſh now their ſcales had beene euener, their Waits truer, and their meaſure larger. They which had ſhut their gates againſt Beggers, begged now themſelues and were not heard, the flames were as deafe as the Sea to thir Wordes, and more raging then his proper nature, being more forceably incenſt with the power which Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone gaue to him. In breefe the ende and effect of Times <hi>Corus</hi> was, that death had ended his Soueragntie, and all liuing creatures were now diſſolued, who had their building &amp; being, either in the earth, ayre, or water, onely now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained.</p>
            <p>The ſeas was to deliuer and yeeld vp her dead whom ſhee had ſwallowed and deuoured,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16824:8"/>
euen all thoſe that had layen ſoaking, and had made their Toombes in her watery boſome, from Noyahs Floude, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Worldes firſt foundation, the earth muſt open her wombe, and giue foorth her children, al duſt, who euer had feeling by the fire of life, and by this light of heauen (reaſon) knew good from ill, muſt with the ſame bodies, the ſame eies, the ſame know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, appeare before this iudgement ſeat, and euerie ſoule receiue his ſentence, according to his owne workes.</p>
            <p>Time hauing thus ended his <hi>Corus,</hi> though not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Stage, the foure Trumpeters ſommoned againe, to awake both the old and new deade from their tedious ſleepe, where while the muſicke ſoundes, and the reſt prepare themſelues ready for entrance, I pray you ſir let me intreat your patience &amp; ſufferance for your further ſatiſfaction, to giue me leaue to ſhew the cauſe why theſe Ieſuits make this or the like play, ere I proceed further to the diſtinguiſhing of it.</p>
            <p>It is not vnknowne to any which know goodneſſe, that theſe Papiſts which falſely tearme themſelues Catholikes, are like the Samaritans, who worſhip God and Idols both together, they profeſſe obedience and practiſe ſedition and rebellion. For what publike warre, or domeſticke tumult hath beene rayſed this many yeares in any parte of Chriſtendom, wherein theſe Ieſu tes haue not borne a princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pall part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? they profeſſe Chaſtitie, and maintain vnc eannes, witneſſe their cuſtome both in allowing and frequenting bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell houſes, they teach voluntar epoue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie, and liue themſelues in coſtly pallaces, yea aduance their Armes aboue the Armes of Princes, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16824:9"/>
outward profeſſion is to ſaue ſoules, but their practiſe to kill ſoules: they call themſelues lights, but make others liue in perpetuall darkeneſſe: they inſinuate themſelues into Princes Courts, and they enter into their ſecrets, where being imbraced, they thriue like Iuie, which deſiſts not till it hath ſuckt the heart out of the moſt nobleſt Oke, they are indeed what badnes can be and ſuch a poyſon, which euery palat ſhould haue iudgment to contemne: they are like the Frogs of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which leapt into all <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Chambers, &amp; Cloſets: they ſwarme euery where l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke lice, and are as noyſome, they ſtir vp wars, and preach the ſlaughter of true Chriſtians, whereſoeuer they come.</p>
            <p>Theſe Wolues as I ſay, in ſhepheards clothing vnder the pretence which they make, they come to feed the flocke, ſatiſfie their rauening purpoſes, and feede vpon it: for ſir this their doctrine is: firſt that it is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e, and he in the ſtate of damnation, vnleſſe hee bee a Fryer, Monke, Ieſuite, or ſome other of their ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to reade the bible tranſlated, eyther into French, Latine or Engliſh without their permiſſion, or to ſay any other prayers, then what are taught &amp; inſtructed by them, that it is ſufficient for a mans ſaluation, to beleeue that which the Romiſh church beleeues, to heare their maſſes, trentals, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rges, to creepe to the croſſe, to pray to the holy virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> mother of chriſt and Queene of heauen, to kneele to their whole peſter of Saintes, to obſerue their faſtings, penance, and pilgrimages, and to obey all their ceremonies, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and traditions, to repeate their ſeueral Auies, and vſe their 7. ſeuerall ſacraments, when Chriſt our true ſchoole maiſter taught but two, and his Apoſtles
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16824:9"/>
as his moſt faithfull Diſciples followed no more, to pray as they pray, to heare as they heare, though they neuer vnderſtand what they heare, what they pray, or what they belieue.</p>
            <p>How the Pope is a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rituall Magiſtrate, and hath a higher degree of authoritie then temporall Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that being inſtalled in his ſanctified ſeate, hee doth preſently repreſent the power &amp; perſon of Ieſus Chriſt, that hee hath power to giue plenarie indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to all men, to diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce with all ſinnes, and for money to pardon, for, without money hee will not doe it, the murther of children, of men, of women, of wiues of neereſt kindred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fornications, adulteries, inceſt, and all abhominations, &amp; with an inſinit rabble, as ſignes, miracles (al which indeed are lies and illuſions) with which they haue lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g blinded the eies of many princes, &amp; ſo poſſeſſed the harts and beleef of many kingdoms, that they cannot now be taught to credite, that there is a mediation, remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, acceſſe to Ieſus Chriſt, or ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation without them, their properties &amp; new fangled inuentions, making his bleſſed ſelfe, and his moſt holy word, who proclaimed to the moſt wretched ſinner, <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are heauy laden, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh you.</hi> And as they haue long corrupted many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo this famous and ancient city Lions, &amp; with ſundrie like ſhewes as this their play of late, ſo dazled the eyes of the multitude, that they cannot ſee beyonde the miſt that theſe haue caſt before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their eares are deafe, their eyes blinde, their memories dull, and their hearts ſo obſtinate, that to conclude, that whatſoeuer is the inuention of thoſe ſeditious impoſtures, is now growne to be the peoples beliefe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16824:10"/>Here withall ſir is to be noted, which let me intreate you to take note of, that all their preachings, playes, &amp; repreſentations, conſiſt of theſe two ſubiects: to make others infamous, and to honor themſelues, to approue the Sea of Rome, the ſole rocke and foundation ouer wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his maſters mouth <hi>Peter</hi> had the charge giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n him, and ſince him for this many hundred years the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and Biſhops of Rome, are the lawful heyres and ſucceſſors, and haue beene carefull fathers, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, foſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rers, and gouernors therof, hauing (as they ſay) like power, and like dominion, though their pride witneſſeth againſt them, they neglect to exerciſe the like doctrine, that hee whoſe faith and confidence was built on them, whoſe obedience and reuerence was payd to them, might perſiſt in what villanie ſoeuer he intended, if but intending to the aduauncement of their church, and the furthering of their ambition (though it ſtretch to the murthering of princes, whom God himſelfe annointed) and the Pope as heauens Vicegerent, had full authoritie to pardon them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them from purgatorie after death, and crowne them with the glories of eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Where on the contrarie ſir, thoſe that are faithfull Chriſtians of them in deriſion, called Lutherans, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonites, Caluiniſts, &amp; Proteſtants, from the word <hi>Proteſt,</hi> meaning they profeſſe much and doe nothing, though we ſerue our maker with vprightneſſe of hart, though wee rob him not of his glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e giuing it to men, though we ſeek as he himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe hath appointed, for no other interceſſor betwixt our ſinnes and the fathers iudgement, but his only begotten ſonne, though as much as lies in the frailtie of mans fleſh to doe, wee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16824:10"/>
his commaundementes, honour our Princes, ſubmit to Magiſtrates, hurt no man willingly, loue our neighbour as ourſelues, yet in their decrees, and not for obeying their inſtitutions, we are the dregges of ſinne, the bubbles of religion, but riſen of late, and ere long to be confounded, we dwell vnder the wrath of heauen, and wee ſhall feele it, we drinke of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſoned cup, and wee ſhall periſh, Angels, Saints and Martyrs haue no fauour with vs, wee are no better then infidels, with whome it is vnlawfull to holde league, and lawfull to breake oath or promiſe, wee are blotted from out the booke of heauen, as wee are excommunicated out of their Church, that we ſhal neuer haue the happineſſe to come to their Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for there is no other locall place ordained for vs then hell, wee are not ſo fortunate as beaſtes, for they liue, die, and then their labours at an ende, but our end is without end, perpetuall deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, as in Bookes of large volumes, they haue publiſhed againſt vs, as in their Sermons they do preach of vs, ſo in this their Play they preſent vs, where by this time if your Worſhippe would bee but pleaſed to thinke, the Trumpeters had left ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that all the dead had aſſumed new life, and were now comming before this Tribunall, I will ſhew as euidently to your iudgement, as it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to my fight, to what ſentence and execution they giue vs Chriſtians, our Princes, Prelates, Gouernours, I, euen vnto the meaneſt: and how they glorifie themſelues from the Cardinall to the Fryar Capochen: may your good Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe but pleaſe to thinke then, that in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16824:11"/>
you are ſeated in Lions, at this time you heard the ſound of excellent muſicke, when preſentlie, as in a ſhew, you beheld all the Popes and Biſhoppes who had gouerned in the papall chaire, ſince the time they profeſſe <hi>Peter</hi> to haue preached there, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of the Romain Empire, vſhered in with conuents of Fryars, companies of Ieſuites colledges of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, indeed of their needfull miniſters of all ſorts, who in their paſſage ſung Anthems, <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and other ſonges of gladnes, euery Pope and Biſhop had his name and title written on his forehead, as thus, ſir: Some but Chriſts vicar, others who inlarged to that Seruant of ſeruants, other King of Kinges, and ſo of their whole ſtile, euen vnto this Pope, which now gouerneth, who though all the reſt were glad to carry themſelues in on their feete, he was borne in on foure Kinges ſhoulders, and as that neither death nor earth, had had power to pull them from their pride, or robes pontificall, ſo though their play was of the generall Seſſions, before which ſhall be a change from all earthlie glories, they came expreſſing the greateſt power and commaund wherein they liued: who when they were all entred vppon the Stage, though they were as proud as Popes are, yet they themſelues with the whole aſſembly made their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance to the vpper iudge, who riſing with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt maieſtie he could ſet, and being adorned gorgeoſly to beget wonder in the ſpectators or beholders ſpake to this purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were the fathers of his church, the ſhepheards of his flocke, to whom hee had giuen doth the keies of heauen &amp; earth, and ful power to bind and looſe mens tranſgreſſions, and hauing founde in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16824:11"/>
his regiſter, they had been faithful in their charge, and careful in his ſeruice, as his beloued on his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he had prepared them a glorious ſeate, and happineſſe euerlaſting, which they entertaining with a Hymne of thankſgiuing, according as hee directed them, in great ſtate ſeated themſelues.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing beheld the Popes and all their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples brought in by the hand of Angels, and placed on the right hand of the throne, may you bee pleaſed ſir, but to turne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your eyes on the left hand, and view the great Turkes, euen from their father <hi>Mahomet,</hi> to him now that raigneth, with Bazzes, Ianizaries, and other inſtruments, adminiſters of his infidelitie, brought in by diuels, and ſeated on the left hand, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Preſter Iohn,</hi> the Emperor of Perſia, and all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes, namely the Kings, and late Queene of England, the king of Denmarke, all thoſe Princes of Germanie that hold faith with vs, <hi>Graue Morris,</hi> and the States of the low Countries: to conclude, they were figured all, that liued contrarie to them in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, though they beleeue in the ſame Chriſt which they profeſſe, yet they rancke them in the number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt infidels, where on the contrary, the Emperor of Germani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, the Kings of France, Spain, &amp; Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, all Dukes and Princes of what prouince ſoeuer, had either their preſence or character, &amp; were placed at the Popes feete, ouer whom hee ſeemed to ſpread his hands and bleſt them, and looking vp towardes him that plaide the Iudge aboue, ſeemed to preſent them as ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> church, and obeyers of his wil, whom he graciouſly ſeeming to accept, there was a Canton ſung of the Angels and Martyrs aboue, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16824:12"/>
knit vp with Maſſe Prieſts, Friers, and the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath: then was from the Popes hand deliuered vnto him that repreſented the ſonne of God, a book wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was ingroſt all pardons, curſes, and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations either for or againſt Princes, or their people, which he deliuering to him that preſented the father, he roſe vp, and bowing to him, intreated him with a ſpeech of interceſſion, to rat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the Popes in his name had executed: the purpoſe of al which was, that they not obeying Rome as the head Church, their Religion as the meanes of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they were now to bee damned without redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which no ſooner aſked, but ſeeming obtained, the Iudge roſe vp to pronounce their ſentence: before which, here Sir you muſt note, that there was many paſſages made of ſeuerall actions, which had hapned in ſeuerall kingdomes, as of ſuch Ieſuites that in ſtirring ſedition, and for moouing Rebellion had loſt their li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, here their deedes was confirmed merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous, and many of them placed in the rancke of Martyrs, what treaſon ſoeuer had beene kindled by them if tending to the dignitie of their Church, both them and the traitors had the ſame benefit. Of which particulars it would be ſomwhat long to write, being two dayes in action, yet (in their due place) I ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to expreſſe ſome of them to you, namely, no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt her late Maieſtie, as of <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rie, Campion, Sommerfield, Ballard, Babbington,</hi> and thoſe fourteene Traitors of that faction, the pretence of <hi>Lopus</hi> to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (conſpiring euen with Iew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite.) In briefe, they were all ſhowne, their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edes approued, and the traitors glorified. The Frier <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16824:12"/>
called <hi>Iames Clement,</hi> that killed <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. king of Frauce, was not here amongſt the number of their prayſes, forgotten, nay they deſcended ſo lowe euen to iuſtifie the late treaſon practiſed againſt our Noble Soueraigne, and his Progenie, to wit, the blowing vp of the Parliament houſe, a practiſe ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and an inuention ſo bloodie, that any man that euer hath heard but the name of God, being aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red of his iudgements, and trembled at hell, would haue bin aſtoniſht to attempt, making it lawfull againſt Gods word to allow of any murthers how euer ſo heynous for their owne benefit.</p>
            <p>Thus hoping ſir, as in a Map, you conceiue a town by the name of it, ſo you will thinke you haue ſeene all the treaſons you haue heard of, practiſed by I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſuites againſt Chriſtian Princes, here at Lions acted, that you haue ſeene the tyrannies of the late Philip king of Spaine deceaſed, by his inquiſition in the Lowe Countri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, the ſlaughtering of the Hollanders, nay his attempts againſt vs in <hi>An. 88.</hi> all preſented either in dumb ſhewes, or in action and their indeuors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: I will onely giue a touch vnto you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> betwixt the Popes and Cardinals, Luther, Caluin, Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and all the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, whom they terme their ſent of Hereſie: the Cathol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke Princes, and the Proteſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Princes, there was ſome argument helde touching th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dignitie of their religion, but you muſt obſerue who preuailed, namely the Romiſh ſide, and I pray you then thinke you behold the Iudge riſing, to pronounce ſentence againſt them, firſt to make his ſpeech mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e terrible, fire was throwne out of his ſeate, noiſes was heard like thunder, in the end, the effect of his ſpeech was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16824:13"/>
this, that for diſobeying the authoritie of the Pope his faithful ſeruant &amp; paſtor of his flock, and the relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing their way to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he as their guide ſhould haue led them vnto, they are now for euer to looſe the ioyes of heauen: which to prepare their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grief, their eyes beheld them in chiefe glory aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d into, and all of them, King, Queene, and ſubiect, to be throwne preſently into hel, to lie on beds of fire which ſhall neuer quench, to be ſtill dying, yet neuer dead, for their pains muſt be euerlaſting: at which <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his whole ſynod of fiends that were beneath, taking his word for a law, firſt tooke hold of the Turks, Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſians, and <hi>Preſter Iohn,</hi> and making ſignes of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, threw them into their hell, ſo as the ages had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded they ſeaze don Chriſtian princes, as namely of our Engliſh kings, <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, whom they na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnder <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the firſt founder of Heretikes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, a prince whoſe life and death was vertuous, and our late Queene of famous memorie, the peacefull gouernes of this kingdome, 44. yeares. the eſtabliſher of Chriſts church, the relieuer of France fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inuaſion of Spaine, &amp; their aſſiſtance the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like league, a comforter of the oppreſſed Chriſtians in Geneua, defendres of the Low Countries, and in deed a pardoner of her enemies: yet theſe Ieſuiticall ſectaries, here in this their play, preſented her, iuſtified the Traitors, and treaſons againſt her, eternized them in her ſight, condemned her by the voyce of their whole Synod to their Hell, &amp; made the figure of her, whoſe charitie was ſo great, neuer but to thinke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully of them, they made a ridiculous obiect to their bald-pate Friers, and a ſcoffing ſpectacle to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16824:13"/>
papiſticall multitude: and as that our gracious Queene, ſo the Kinges of Denmarke, the Princes of Germanie, the States of the low Countries, in briefe all as aforeſaid, were by theſe Ieſuits decree throwne downe into their hell (and imbraſt by diuels beneath) while the other ſeemed to reioyce aboue.</p>
            <p>But ſee the iudgement of the true God, that euen in the height of their reioyſings, whilſt theſe Ieſuites made aſcorne and contempt of the Chriſtians, whilſt they made falſe thundrings, &amp; falſe lightnings, while they directed to the people that now were the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans and Hugonites, burning in perpetual torments, now were they ſhreeking and not heard, nowe were lamenting and not regarded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as they were, ſhould all mankind be that forſooke their religion, and built not their ſaluations vpon them: our true God as I ſay, good ſir, who rules the cloudes with his becke, who though he winks yet ſleeps not, ſeeing this their preſumption, and in his vpright iuſtice not longer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that his name ſhould be prophaned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his ſeate v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, his iudgements abuſed, out of his Quiuer of wrath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and armor of fire, whom no mortall man can reſiſt, drew one arrow to ſtrike them downe, who ſo rebelliouſly roſe vp againſt him.</p>
            <p>For here ſir, I pray you take knowledge, at the time when this Ieſuite gaue his ſentence <hi>ite maledicti,</hi> and their fained diuel began to ſeaſe on Chriſtians, the day was as cleere &amp; as hopefull as a huſband man would deſire in harueſt, when in a minut one darke cloude as the forerunner of his true Maſters will vſhered by fire &amp; attended by darknes making eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that which was but now the height of the day as pitchy &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16824:14"/>
fearefull as the blackeſt night, when preſently the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hauing ſcarſe time to thinke of amazement, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der forerun with lightning, being heauens ordinance ſhot off, and ſtroke from his ſeate he that preſumed to take his name vpon him, the Ieſuite aſſumed to bee his ſonne, and ſhee that preſented ſo boldly, the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and he that would afore his time, play <hi>Lucifer</hi> the Prince of Diuels.</p>
            <p>Here ſir, may you behold (what I beheld) the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, againſt theſe arrogating Iudges, they that but a minute ſince would make vſe of their breath (ordained to glorifie their maker) to be a help to make wordes to condemne others, and they that would make hee giuen from heauen as a helpefull Officer for mans neceſſities, to be a tormentor of them, are now with fire from heauen in the ſame twinckling, (whileſt their glorie ſtood at the higheſt) ſtruck down from their ſeate, depriued of their breath, and depoſed of all, at the pleaſure of the higheſt, to what place, far be it from me to iudge, for by any inſtructions, I could ſtay to receiue, for the haſt I had to Franckforde, they were carried away, and while my reſidence there, not heard of: but to giue you further notice of what I ſaw, I am bolde to proceede, and to ſignifie, as the day was on a ſodaine darkened, ſo after the thunder had ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken the power of his wrath, it was as ſodenly cleare, when my ſelf as the reſt of the ſpectators, might behold the toppe of their Celledge, ouer the throne torn with the thunder, their new erected Gods, and hee that aſſumed the Diuell not to be ſeene, at which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty eye being driuen into amazement, by flight ſought to preſerue themſelues, in which preſſe for ſafetie, ſeuen
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16824:14"/>
more found daunger being there ſmothered to death, and all comming forth into the Citie, found heauen to haue powred downe ſuch aboundance of raine, that the Citie ſeemed halfe drowned, where many, what with labouring to conuay out the water, tooke ſurfeits with heate, and others by intemperance of cold, which ſo much water bred, had ingedred in their bodies, ſuch coughes and Agues, that by the ſecond rod of heauen, many haue beene ſent to their graues. Thus much I can certifie you ſir to be of credite and truth. And for the ſtrangeneſſe, thought it my dutie to command vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, which as it is a wonderfull iudgement of God, to abate the pride of theſe Romiſh Prieſtes, and rabble of the ſeditious, who put their confidence in the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> their truſt in Saints, and in the merits of their owne workes (and indeede the ouerthrow of their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie) ſo ſhould it be as a preſeruatiue, ſent both to ours and other Nations, to ſee that their wordes are deceit, their religion poyſon, and ſo contemn both them and it: where on the contrarie, it is a comfort and a confirmation of vs in our Chriſtian faith and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, and in him onely to put our truſt.</p>
            <p>Sir if at the receit of your next Letters, I ſhall find this abſtract of their play ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto you in this diſcours acceptaple, I ſhall not faile in my next buſineſſe in a larger maner to recommend vnto you the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof, both in the acts and ſcenes, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it, which from a Gentleman of Lions, whome I haue ſome intereſt in, and he the like in the Ieſuitical Colledge, I am promiſed to receiue, if either it may be a pleaſure to me, or deſired of your worſhip, till when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16824:15"/>
ſir, not to trouble you with other particular occurrents which happened by the inundation of thoſe waters.</p>
            <p>I will only giue you to vnderſtand, that what through the alteration this ſtraunge play<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath bred in mens minds, and the diſeaſes the cold hath ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in their bodies, at what priuate meeting ſoeuer happened betwixt any of their Church and ours, there is little conference had, but about this their late play, and the iudgements which God in his vprightneſſe ſent vnto them, all of our faith affirming that being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſt France for the murder intended by a merchants ſon named <hi>Chaſtle</hi> a ſcholler of the Ieſuits, and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated thereunto by a Ieſuit named <hi>Giniarda</hi> Ieſuit to the Colledge of Clerimount in Parris, that firſt it partly appeared by the lawfulnes of the cauſe for which they were expulſt, that it was as vnlawfull for them to returne, but it was euident by the Iuſtice which God himſelfe ſhewed vpon them (in that means wherein they begun to build themſelues a new foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and to outreach the pride which heretofore they had growne vnto (namely to arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues his diuine power, &amp; his ſupreme preheminence) they are members ſo dangerous, and their doctrineſo ſeditious, that they are vnſit ſubiectes to haue hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in any Chriſtian common wealth, where on the contrarie, both they and their diſciples alſo continuing obſtinate (as that is a point of their doctrine, which they faile not to ground men in) they doe not with modeſtie ſeeme to excuſe them in their hereſies, but as preſumptuouſtie, as if this blow of heauen had not wakte them, they both confirme them, and as conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue in them, which difference in that parte of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16824:15"/>
France, cauſeth mens mindes much to bee troubled, doubting what the ſucceſſe will attaine vnto, ſome doubting it will grow to a publike tumult, the leaſt looking for priuate quarrels, and the rather becauſe theſe conferences hauing beene often, and in ſeuerall places, bordering in &amp; about Lions, many of theirown church haue ſince vpon priuate confideration had, both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; their religion, declinde themſelues from them, to the great comfort both of vs that are Marchants, &amp; all Chriſtians in France, whereby we likewiſe conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belieue, that this is a certaine preſagement, that ere long the glory of their Romiſh pride will conclude, and no doubt as it is a comfort here in France, it will be no leſſe to all loyall Engliſhmen with you, and this ſigne which heauen ſent to their ouerthrow, will be a booke for Gentlemen and ſubiects of all ſorts, from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt to read their follies in, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth not to be ſeduced to build their faiths vpon their opinions, to be forward in their dangerous enterpriſes to the ouerthrow of their auncient houſes, and moſt worthie families.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir both now and after I ſhall heare from you, beſtowing my time carefully &amp; induſtriouſly in your affaires, and omitting no occaſions for the recouerie of thoſe monies before mentioned. I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From Franckford, your Worſhips Factor, R. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
